<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>kitofr.github.io</title>
    <description>This blog will (hopefully) be a colleciton of my ideas and reflections about topics like politics, programming, change, health
</description>
    <link>http://kitofr.github.io/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://kitofr.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <pubDate>Wed, 03 Feb 2016 16:59:33 +0100</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 03 Feb 2016 16:59:33 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v2.4.0</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Practice, practice and more practice!</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;imagine-this&quot;&gt;Imagine this.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You have a professional soccer team. The average player costs around $ 35 000 000. 
They have rocket high salaries and you need to acquire more money every month just
to keep em playing.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, you bought them for a &lt;em&gt;decent&lt;/em&gt; price, and you would like to get some kick back
of your investment in the long term. Maybe, that means you would like to win the 
series, sell of some of them at the end of the season etc. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To protect your team and investment, you don’t want them to become injured, sick 
or depressed. You’ve actually gone so far as to hire a nutritionist, doctor, 
chiropractor and various other people to make sure they stay &lt;em&gt;on top of their game&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During game time you have the best coaches money can buy. They also have an extra
team of scouts, looking for new talent and scouting the competition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You have approximately 3 ways of generating money off your team.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Your players generate money through playing games. Cup, series and friendly games.
That is where their value is reevaluated and you win price money. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Your team becomes successful and the value of the team rises.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Advertising during game play on television.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Now imagine you banned practice.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;ALL PRACTICE&lt;/strong&gt;
All players need to play games. All the time. If someone wanted to &lt;em&gt;practice&lt;/em&gt; on something,
the player need to ensure it does not interfere with eating and resting schedules. It 
has to be &lt;em&gt;off hours&lt;/em&gt;. Should not interfere with the rest off the team.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your motivation for this would be:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Practice does not generate any money. It does not raise the value of the players, because they are only evaluated
while playing. The team doesn’t &lt;em&gt;win&lt;/em&gt; anything during practice, nor can you sell
any advertising on television during practice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;wait-say-what&quot;&gt;WAIT… say WHAT?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most people coming into any profession knows that there’s a path to excellence in
that area. There’s no question that soccer players like &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Zlatan_Ibrahimovi%C4%87&quot;&gt;Zlatan&lt;/a&gt;, 
artists like &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Madonna_(entertainer)&quot;&gt;Madonna&lt;/a&gt;, painters, chess players et al
 do some kind of practice to keep their game sharp.
As a matter of fact. Practice is &lt;strong&gt;most&lt;/strong&gt; of what they do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;me-as-an-example&quot;&gt;Me as an example&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I grew up I used to play the guitar. After a couple of years fiddling, I became 
quite good. I ended up going to school at &lt;a href=&quot;http://sodralatinsgymnasium.stockholm.se/&quot;&gt;Södra Latins Gymnasium&lt;/a&gt;
in Stockholm, playing the classical guitar. During my years there I practiced about 3-8 hours per day. Every day. All week. 
For 3 years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In comparison to that, I think I did around 20 concerts. I played in various ensembles, a guitar quartet, and solo.
Most pieces range between 3-5 minutes of play. Which would roughly total a hefty 60-120 min of 
&lt;em&gt;game play&lt;/em&gt;. 1 to 2 hours in 3 years!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think some mathematics would be suitable here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Say I was a lazy student. Practicing only the bare minimum and hitting around 2 hour day.
That would give 14 hours per week. 50 weeks per year (hey you need some breaks as well right?)
would give 700 hours per year. For 3 years, 2100 hours. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oh, so that ratio is quite interesting. Even for a lazy student. &lt;strong&gt;1-2 hours of game per 
2100 hours of practice!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now I know per fact that most professional musicians practice around 4-8 hours per day.
Most of them have done so since they were 4-6 years old. I also know that a lot of the
professional athletes, artists out there are in the same ball park. Most of them, specially 
athletes, don’t &lt;em&gt;race&lt;/em&gt; more than a couple of times per year, and at a fraction of the 
practice time&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:races&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:races&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-dysfunction-of-the-everyday-company&quot;&gt;The dysfunction of the everyday company&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“It doesn’t make sense to hire smart people and then tell them what to do; we hire smart people so they can tell us what to do. - Steve Jobs”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think there’s something hidden between the lines in that quote. I believe Steve 
expect smart people to practice. I believe that is as given as gravity. 
Without practice skills degenerate. You don’t advance and motivation falters. 
Smart people know that they need to sharpen their knifes. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Given this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;How come we don’t practice&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:practice&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:practice&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; at work?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;How come, most programmers I know (me included) are only &lt;em&gt;“half good”&lt;/em&gt; at touch typing?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What would happen if not practicing, say 80% of the time, was considered misconduct&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:misconduct&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:misconduct&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;i-spy-problems&quot;&gt;I spy problems&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;individual-expertise&quot;&gt;Individual expertise&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;team-practice&quot;&gt;Team practice&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;addition-notes&quot;&gt;Addition notes&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I notice that once again I will have to come back to this inquiry to exploit it even further. 
Especially some parts that are left out. Degradation of learned skills without further practice, 
organizational wide practice and motivation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:races&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Most athletes also do practice races. So that they prepare for the ones they really want to win, with as similar conditions as possible. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:races&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:practice&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Yes I know, good people practice, but that mostly occur &lt;em&gt;after hours&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:practice&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:misconduct&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;It would be for Zlatan remember? &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:misconduct&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 03 Feb 2016 16:59:32 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://kitofr.github.io/2016/02/03/practice_make_perfekt.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://kitofr.github.io/2016/02/03/practice_make_perfekt.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>How to balance your team</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;This time around I want to dwell into how to tackle teams that are
not yielding, collaborating or has some other dysfunction. Let us dig in to it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve had this idea for quite some time now, that teams needs to be balanced to perform at their peak.
Much like a sports team. So lets take a detour into lacrosse land. I was thinking soccer first, but that’s to boring. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;some-background-on-lacrosse-httpsenwikipediaorgwikilacrosse--first&quot;&gt;Some background on &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lacrosse&quot;&gt;Lacrosse&lt;/a&gt; first.&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lacrosse is a ball game played on a big green turf, with 10 players in each team. 
The team roughly consists of 1 goalie, 3 defenders, 3 mid fielders (midies) and 3 attack men.
The goal of the game is to toss a rubber ball into the goal of the other team more times
than them. Simple. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To ‘toss’ a ball in lacrosse you need a stick. Different positions 
of the team requires different sticks. For example, the goalie has a large head on his 
stick, making it easier to catch balls. The defenders has longer sticks, which gives them
reach. Midies and attackers have short sticks, good for quick release and protection of the
ball.
Obviously different positions require a different skill set for best performance. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;goalies&quot;&gt;Goalies&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A goalie needs to have quite the reflexes and be a decent commander, as he yells out 
ball position and various strategies to the defense. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;defenders&quot;&gt;Defenders&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Defenders need be quick at backward pacing, good at checking sticks and reading out 
weak players. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;mid-fielders&quot;&gt;Mid fielders&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Midies are the working dogs of the field. They play on both ends of the field, thus they require
stamina and endurance, as well as the skill to carry the ball from the defensive end to attack. 
They also need to know how execute the defensive as well as the offensive strategies agreed upon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;attackers&quot;&gt;Attackers&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Attackers need to be accurate and extremely quick handling the ball and shooting. 
They also need to learn offensive strategies and read their defenders. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;balancing-in-lacrosse&quot;&gt;Balancing in lacrosse&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is quite easy to see that different persons fit into a lacrosse team at various spots. It’s not
always obvious where you have the best fit for a single person, but given the opponents strengths
and weaknesses you should be able to read how to best position your team. 
As a coach you train your team to become as good as possible at their position, specialty and skills.
You also challenge them to switch up, try different things and learn what is going on
at a different location of the field. This will make them more resilient and broaden their 
understanding of the game.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-dysfunction-in-the-corporate-world&quot;&gt;The dysfunction in the corporate world&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ever had a coach, coworker or even a boss ask you to switch places with someone in 
a different area of the company?
Ever seen a developer being asked to take the lead in a sales meeting?
I sure haven’t. I know I would be scared as hell. And now when we are on the subject.
&lt;em&gt;WHY IS THAT?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My initial take is that I have never ever seen that part of the field. I don’t even know 
the rules of that part of the game. &lt;em&gt;Might even score in the wrong goal.&lt;/em&gt;
It is like we, and now I am talking about my extended team the Corporation, playing 
a totally different game divided on different departments of the company. The only
&lt;em&gt;link&lt;/em&gt; between the teams are the executives or the like. &lt;em&gt;It’s like a bad telephone
game with different goals and different rules on every ear.&lt;/em&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-to-address-poor-company-posture&quot;&gt;How to address poor company posture&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;play-the-same-game&quot;&gt;Play the same game&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Start with aligning your company to play the same game. This is number one. 
Remove all blind folds and clearly state the rules and goals for each part of your 
game field. Make sure that everybody knows how to play and assist driving the ball from A-&amp;gt;B at
any given position. This will ensure that if the ball gets dropped, anyone can pick
it up and pass it along to the most suitable player.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;understand-your-team&quot;&gt;Understand your team&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While playing the same game, repositioning people and letting them to get to know the
tactics and goals, you and they will discover weaknesses and strengths that you didn’t 
know about. Use that to your advantage. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;practice-the-game&quot;&gt;Practice the GAME&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am a firm believer that we practice to little. I will address that in another post. 
But make sure your situation is set up in a way that you can practice safely, making
a lot of mistakes and learn how to address them. Remember, the goal is not to get all
your team mates to be best at every position, merely to know how to play that part.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;additional-notes&quot;&gt;Additional notes&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I realize that even how much I ever wanted to, I would not be able to write an exhaustive 
post on this matter, because it is to grand. However; the aim is to give some pointers and
hopefully come back to this from another angle later on.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 03 Feb 2016 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://kitofr.github.io/2016/02/03/how_do_you_balance_your_team.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://kitofr.github.io/2016/02/03/how_do_you_balance_your_team.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Hello</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;So, I realized I wanted to start writing again. 
Not that I’ve been an extensive writer in the past, but 
I ideas keep popping up that I want to write down. Hence,
this blog.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;OK, now as we got that figured out; what the heck am I going to blog about?
As mentioned, different inquiries keep coming back to me. Philosophical, technical
and various other subjects, such as health, learning, motivation. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hope you enjoy can inspire me to write more, and gain better insights on the subject
at hand. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cheers,
Kristoffer&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 03 Feb 2016 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://kitofr.github.io/2016/02/03/hello.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://kitofr.github.io/2016/02/03/hello.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
